Okay בוקר טוב Boker Tov today's דף daf is ק״ד Kuf Daled
104 we pick up at the bottom of ק״ג עמוד ב׳ Kuf
Gimmel Amud Bet three lines from the bottom אמר רבי יוחנן משום
רבי יוסי בן קיסמא Amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi Yosei ben Kisma
and we are dealing now with of course the whole discussion about
which kings and which commoners do not have a portion in the
world to come and why some of them people that were totally
wicked in our history were not mentioned and included in the list
and the last person we were talking about was why מיכה Michah
wasn't included in the list and the גמרא Gemara said because he
you know he made his food available to passersby and for that
reason he was not included in the list so let's pick up
with that point אמר רבי יוחנן משום רבי יוסי בן קיסמא גדולה
לגימה Amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi Yosei ben Kisma Gedola Legima great
is a tasting of food and extending of
food שהרחיקה שתי משפחות מישראל shehirchika shtei mishpachot miYisrael that it pushed
away two families in Israel שנאמר shene'emar or from Israel I should
say שנאמר על דבר אשר לא קדמו אתכם בלחם ובמים shene'emar al
devar asher lo kidmu etchem balechem uvamayim that עמון ומואב Amon u'Moav
you know we can't they can't marry into Jews because they did
not greet us with bread and water so that simple act of
not greeting with bread and water you know caused a whole distancing
of these two nations that were right on the border of Israel
okay רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan it could also be that they were
close because we are related to them through לוט Lot but anyway
רש״י Rashi for reasons that are coming up will say the closeness
here means sort of geographically close on our
border רבי יוחנן דידיה אמר Rabbi Yochanan dideih amar Rabbi Yochanan on
his own said that even expanded this teaching מרחקת את הקרובים meracheket
et hakrovim that it can distance those who are close what we
just said ומקרבת את הרחוקים umikarrevet et harichokim and if you do
it properly you extend food to someone who needs it it brings
those that are distant close ומעלמת עיניים מן הרשעים uma'alemet einayim min
harisha'im
and it makes God turn a blind eye from the wicked that
the evil are doing ומשרה שכינה על נביאי הבעל umashra Shechinah al
nevi'ei habaal and it even has the power that a prophet of
the בעל Baal of עבודה זרה avodah zarah that God the divine
spirit will rest on that person for the merit of extending food
ששגגתו עולה זדון sheshigagato olah zadon
and if somebody the negligence about not doing this will be held
accountable to it as if it was intentional now we're going to
unpack that very nice little compact statement מרחקת את הקרובים meracheket et
hakrovim so it distances those that were close top of ק״ד עמוד
א׳ Kuf Daled Amud Alef מעמון ומואב me'Amon u'Moav עמון ומואב Amon
u'Moav as we just said it's an explicit פסוק pasuk
ומקרבת את הרחוקים umikarrevet et harichokim brings close those that were distant
מיתרו miYitro this is from יתרו Yitro דאמר רבי יוחנן d'amar Rabbi
Yochanan בשכר קראן לו ויאכל לחם bischar kir'an lo veyochal lechem in
rewards for יתרו Yitro telling his daughters to call משה Moshe and
to give him food זכו בני בניו וישבו בלשכת הגזית zachu benei
banav veyashvu belishkat hagazit his descendants ultimately merited and they were judges
in Israel and they sat in the לשכת הגזית Lishkat HaGazit the
סנהדרין Sanhedrin right in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash שנאמר וממשפחות סופרים
ישבי יעבץ shene'emar umimishpachot sofrim yoshvei Yavetz and from the family of
the scribes the dwellers of Yavetz תרעתים שמעתים שוכתים Tiratim Shimatim Suchatim
these are the various names המה הקינים hemah hakeinim here's the key
line so they are סופרים sofrim first of all and they're scribes
and the גמרא Gemara understands that this means you know sitting in
the סנהדרין Sanhedrin and they are הקינים הבאים מחמת אבי בית רכב
hakeinim haba'im mechamat avi beit Rechav that come from Chamath the father
of Beit Rechav וכתיב התם u'chtiv hatam and who are these קינים
keinim ובני קיני חתן משה uvnei Keini chotein Moshe the sons of
the Keini Moshe's father-in-law so קיני Keini is a descendant of יתרו
Yitro okay עלו מעיר התמרים alu me'ir hatemarim they went up from
the city of palms את בני יהודה et benei Yehudah with the
children of Yehudah מדבר יהודה midbar Yehudah towards the desert of Yehudah
אשר בנגב ערד asher banegev Arad that's in the
south וילך וישב את העם vayelech vayeshev et ha'am they went and
they dwelt with the people okay so and so it
described עמון ומואב Amon u'Moav as close and יתרו Yitro as far
those that were close it pushed away and those that were far
it drew near so why was יתרו Yitro far so because one
explanation as I've been saying is he was geographically far עמון ומואב
Amon u'Moav were geographically close the other approach would be to read
it as in terms of relatives עמון ומואב Amon u'Moav were relatives
they were descendant from לוט Lot and they were pushed away and
יתרו Yitro wasn't our relative and he was brought close but רש״י
Rashi doesn't like that explanation because he says that you know he
understands that יתרו Yitro was descended from בני קטורה benei Keturah you
know that came מדין Midyan and that came יתרו Yitro so he
sees that יתרו Yitro was actually from the family ultimately going back
to אברהם Avraham so he reads it geographically okay continuing on so
that's pushing bringing those that are far away closer
ומעלמת עיניים מן הרשעים uma'alemet einayim min harisha'im it causes God to
turn a blind eye from the wicked ממיכה miMichah that was from
מיכה Michah that's what we said that's why you know he's not
counted here in the
list ומשרה שכינה umashra Shechinah על נביאי הבעל al nevi'ei habaal
from the friend, the colleague, not really the friend of עדו הנביא.
Iddo HaNavi. עדו הנביא Iddo HaNavi was a true prophet and there
was somebody else who was a prophet of the בעל Baal and
he was and he was sort of deceiving עדו Iddo and he
caused him to come to his house and he fed him food.
All right and
דכתיב dechtiv the פסוק pasuk says ויהי הם יושבים אל השולחן vayehi
hem yoshvim el hashulchan and they, עדו Iddo and this false prophet,
were sitting on the table ויהי דבר השם אל הנביא אשר השיבו
vayehi devar Hashem el hanavi asher heshivo and the word of God
came to this prophet, this prophet of the בעל. Baal. Okay, so
now it might have been obviously for a particular need but the
fact that God is speaking directly to him see how powerful it
is extending food to somebody who is in need. All right ושיגגת
תלמוד עולה
זדון v'shigegat talmud olah zadon last one, and even negligence about not
doing it is treated as you're culpable as if you did it
willfully דאמר רב יהודה אמר רב d'amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav
says רב יהודה Rav Yehuda in the name of רב Rav אלמלא
הלווהו יהונתן לדוד שתי ככרות לחם ilmale hilvehu Yehonatan l'David shtei kikrot
lechem if יהונתן Yehonatan had just given דוד David when דוד David
was running away from שאול Shaul two loaves of bread then think
of all the tragedy that would have been prevented because it caused
דוד David didn't have food, he went to נוב Nov the city
of כהנים, kohanim, which led to שאול Shaul wiping them out and
דואג Doeg getting to slander and ultimately because of that sin שאול
Shaul was killed and none of this would have happened if דוד
David had just been given food from יהונתן. Yehonatan. So see the
cost of it even though it was just an issue of negligence.
So אלמלא הלווהו יהונתן לדוד שתי ככרות לחם ilmale hilvehu Yehonatan l'David
shtei kikrot lechem if יהונתן Yehonatan had only lent דוד David or
given two loaves of bread לא נהרגה נוב עיר הכהנים lo neherga
Nov ir hakohanim the נוב Nov city of כהנים kohanim would not
have been wiped out by שאול Shaul ולא נטרד דואג אדומי v'lo
nitrad Doeg Adomi and דואג אדומי Doeg Adomi who told the, slandered
דוד David at that time would not have been killed as a
result ולא נהרג שאול ושלושת בניו v'lo neherag Shaul v'shloshet banav and
שאול Shaul and his children who died as a result of that
sin that would not have happened either. Okay
and excuse me I misstated it but by the case of דואג
Doeg it's when it says ולא נטרד דואג אדומי v'lo nitrad Doeg
Adomi it doesn't mean that he was killed but it means that
because of his sin of slandering דוד David he was נטרד, nitrad,
he was excluded from the עולם הבא. olam haba. So he would
not have done his sin, he would not have been excluded from
the עולם הבא olam haba and שאול Shaul would not have done
his sin and the city wouldn't be wiped out and then שאול
Shaul and his sons would not have been wiped out. Okay so
that's the end of that discussion about מיכה Micha and led us
to this digression about the importance of extending food to those who
need.
ומפני מה לא מנו את אחז u'mipnei ma lo manu et Achaz
so now let's deal with other evil kings in Israel. Why was
אחז Achaz not listed? אמר רבי ירמיה בר אבא amar Rabbi Yirmiyah
bar Abba מפני שמוטל בין שני צדיקים בין יותם לחזקיהו mipnei shemutal
bein shenei tzaddikim bein Yotam l'Chizkiyahu because he was the son of
יותם Yotam and the father of חזקיהו. Chizkiyahu. עוזיה יותם אחז חזקיהו
Uziyah Yotam Achaz Chizkiyahu right so that's the list, so יותם אחז
חזקיהו Yotam Achaz Chizkiyahu so because of his father and because of
his son. Now does that mean that therefore he will get עולם
הבא olam haba because of his good father and his good son
or is the question really here לא מנו? lo manu? When we
are going to list and identify them who are the people we
want to call out? And we'll see about this coming up right
how do we ultimately know who does and doesn't get and when
we gave the list of the three kings and the four הדיוטות
hedyotot are we saying this is exhaustive or are we really calling
them out and somehow חז"ל chazal knew that it was exactly these
three kings and those four הדיוטות. hedyotot. So one way to read
this is that it was chosen not to list him because of
the honor of his father and his son, not that that means
that he will get עולם הבא. olam haba. All right let's keep
that in mind. Okay. רב יוסף אמר Rav Yosef amar מפני שהיה
לו בושת פנים מישעיהו mipnei shehayah lo boshet panim mi'Yeshayahu because he
had shame from ישעיהו Yeshayahu because he knew of his sin and
he at least was able to feel shame when he saw ישעיהו.
Yeshayahu. שנאמר ויאמר השם אל ישעיהו צא נא לקראת אחז אתה ושאר
ישוב בנך shene'emar vayomer Hashem el Yeshayahu tze na likrat Achaz ata
u'She'ar Yashuv bnecha and the פסוק pasuk says ויאמר השם אל ישעיהו
vayomer Hashem el Yeshayahu צא נא לקראת אחז tze na likrat Achaz
אתה
ושאר ישוב בנך ata u'She'ar Yashuv bnecha you and שאר ישוב She'ar
Yashuv your son אל קצה תעלת הבריכה העליונה el ktze te'alat habreicha
ha'elyona by the edge of this upper pool אל מסילת שדה כובס
el mesilat sdeh kovess by the path by the field of where
they do the laundry. מאי כובס mai kovess so what does it
mean why is it pointing out the field of כובס, kovess, the
laundry? איכא דאמרי דכבשינהו לאפיה ika d'amrei d'chavshinehu l'apei it means that
he buried his face. When he saw ישעיהו Yeshayahu he hid his
face out of embarrassment וחלף v'chalaf and he went away.
ואיכא דאמרי אוכלא דקצרי סחפא ארישא וחלף v'ika d'amrei uchla d'katzrei sachpa
areisha v'chalaf no a sprinkling thing used by to sprinkle water or
to sprinkle incense used by launderers by cleaners. So that was the
כובס koves and that he put that on his head to cover
his, like a mask to cover his head, and he left. So
he was embarrassed from ישעיהו. Yeshayahu. So that sounds like it's more
that why he's got a merit the world to come, not why
it's a question of whether he was just included in the list
or not. Okay, this at least showed he had shame. מפני מה
לא מנו את אמון? mipnei ma lo manu et Amon? Why did
they not list Amon also an evil king? מפני כבודו של יאשיהו.
mipnei kevodo she-Yoshiyahu. So because of the honor of Yoshiyahu, because Yoshiyahu
was the son of, of Amon. And Yoshiyahu was a righteous king.
So מנשה נמי לא נמני Menashe nami lo nimnei if that's true
why should we not count Menashe? Menashe is definitely on the list.
Why should we not count Menashe? מפני כבודו של
חזקיהו mipnei kevodo shel Chizkiyahu because of the honor of Chizkiyahu because
Chizkiyahu was his father. So if somebody is not going to be
mentioned on the list because of the son, then somebody also because
they had a righteous son, somebody also shouldn't be mentioned, you know,
because they had a righteous father. So the Gemara says, famous Gemara,
it says ברא מזכי אבא אבא לא מזכי ברא. bra mazakei aba
aba lo mazakei bra. The son brings merit to the father, the
father doesn't bring merit to the son. Which makes sense. You know,
you're a good father, you know, somebody is a bad person and
they've got a good father, why should they get credit, they get
a little bit of a free ride because their father is so
good? They're bad, they didn't even learn from their good father. So
that's the father's not מזכה mezake the son. But the son is
מזכה mezake the father. If somebody is a bad person but has
a good son, so that son at least reflects well something positive
back on the father. Alright, so again this question is is it
that why they were, you know, is that, does that mean that
they merited and they will get the world to come because they
had a good son or is this just to get a reason
why he wasn't explicitly included in the list? Anyway, so now, so
it sounds here like it's more substantive about whether he had the
merit. Now, now we're going to sort of show, continue with this
statement.
דכתיב de-chtiv as the פסוק pasuk says ואין מידי מציל, ve-ein mi-yadi
matzil, no one can save from me. אין אברהם מציל את ישמעאל
ואין יצחק מציל את עשו. ein Avraham matzil et Yishmael ve-ein Yitzchak
matzil et Esav.
A good father will not be able to protect a bad son.
Avraham can't save Yishmael, Yitzchak can't save Esav. So Chizkiyahu was not
able, his merit could not protect Menashe. Okay, but the opposite would
work that the merit of Yoshiyahu the son would protect the, the
father Amon.
So now the Gemara says השתא דאתית להכי, hashta de-atit le-hachi, now
that we're saying that the merit of the son can work for
the father that he won't be included in the list, so אחז
נמי לא נמני, Achaz nami lo nimnei, we can explain that the
reason that Achaz wasn't counted was משום כבודו של חזקיהו mishum kevodo
shel Chizkiyahu because Chizkiyahu was his son and he had such a
righteous son. So rather than the reason we said before that he
had showed shame, and that's why, here it's because he had a
righteous son. Okay. מפני מה לא מנו את יהויקים? mipnei ma lo
manu et Yehoyakim? And why did they not count Yehoyakim? Now there
were plenty of evil kings for Israel, but the Gemara is identifying
the ones that it considers to be, you know, really, really particularly
evil, you know they were like linked earlier to this whole פסוק
pasuk about, about,
about like the, you know I walked by the field of a
lazy person and it all filled with thorns and the Gemara specifically
focused on kings that it was particularly evil and those are the
ones that they are going through right now to ask why were
they not included in the list.
מפני מה לא מנו את יהויקים? mipnei ma lo manu et Yehoyakim?
משום דרבי חייא בר אבין mishum de-Rabbi Chiya bar Avin because of
the story of Rabbi Chiya bar Avin. דאמר רבי חייא בר אבין
de-amar Rabbi Chiya bar Avin and we've had this
גמרא Gemara earlier כתיב אגולגלתיה דיהויקים ktiv a-gulgaltia de-Yehoyakim it was written
on the skull of Yehoyakim זאת ועוד אחרת. zot ve-od acheret. This
and one more. You know he had been, the Torah, the פסוק
pasuk had said that you won't be buried, you know, you'll be
buried like a donkey, you know, you'll have the burial of a
donkey meaning you won't be buried, and here we're saying that curse
and one more. What does that mean?
So זקנו דרבי פרידא zekano de-Rabbi Preida the grandfather of Rabbi Preida
which is the same Rabbi Chiya we just mentioned, אשכח גולגלתא ashkach
gulgata he found this skull דהוה שדי בשערי ירושלים de-hava shadei be-sha'arei
Yerushalayim that was cast aside at the gates of Jerusalem. That's what
it says about Yehoyakim that your body will be cast in the
gates of Jerusalem. וכתיב בה ve-chtiv bah and it was written on
it זאת ועוד אחרת. zot ve-od acheret.
This horrible thing happened and one more. קברה kavrah he buried it.
He didn't yet know what it meant, he know it was a
bizarre statement, a bizarre writing. He buried the skull ולא איקברא ve-lo
ikbara it wouldn't stay buried, it popped back up. קברה kavrah he
tried to bury it again ולא איקברא ve-lo ikbara it wouldn't stay
buried. אמר amar so then he realized what he was dealing with.
גולגלתיה דיהויקים היא. gulgaltia de-Yehoyakim hi. This must be the skull of
Yehoyakim. דכתיב ביה de-chtiv beih it's written by it קבורת חמור יקבר
kvurat chamor yikaver the burial of a donkey he'll be buried סחוב
והשלך sachov ve-hashlech you know cast away, discarded and and therefore he
can never really get a proper burial. אמר amar so he said
okay, מלכא הוא malka hu he even if he can't be buried
it's still the you know the body, the the skeleton, the skull
of a king, ולא איכשר לזלזולי ביה, velo ikshar lezalzulei beih, and
it's still not proper to treat him with in this degrading fashion;
כרכיה בשיראי, karkhei beshirai, he wrapped it with silk ואותבה בסיפתא ve'otva
besifta and he put it in a box to keep it protect,
at least he can't bury it, but at least it shouldn't get
kicked around. חזיתיה דבתיה, chaziteih devatayeih, the wife saw this
skull, it's alas poor Yorick. סברה האי איתתא קמייתא, savra hadi itseta
kamayeta, she thought that this must be his first wife, and in
a different version of the story her neighbor said it must be
his first wife דהא לא קא מנשי לה, dehalo ka menashe lah,
he can't forget about his first wife so he's keeping her skull
in this box. So she got very jealous, שגרה תנורא, shagra tannura,
she fired up the oven, וקלתיה, vekaltzeih, and she burned it. היינו
דכתיב זאת ואחרת, hainu dechtiv zot ve'acheret, and then he understood what
it means this you won't get a normal burial and another terrible
thing will happen, you will be completely incinerated, your body. Because of
that harsh punishment, that's why he wasn't included. Again, does that mean
that that's why we're not going to list him, or does that
mean that that's why we won't say or that's why he genuinely
will have a portion of the world to come? It's not clear.
תני, tani, we learned in a Braisa, first of the middle-sized lines.
אמר רבי שמעון בן אלעזר, amar Rabbi Shimon Ben Elazar, בשביל הטוב
בעיניך עשיתי, bishvil hatov be'einecha asiti, now that we're talking about kings
and we mentioned חזקיהו Chizkiyahu as a good king, we have to
point we're going to point out some things about him that weren't
so good. When חזקיהו Chizkiyahu was going to die and he prayed
to השם, Hashem, he got sick and he thought he was going
to die and he prayed to השם Hashem and he said God,
I did everything that I was supposed to, I did what was
right in your eyes, please let me live,
and then the prophet comes and tells him God heard your prayer,
you'll live, you'll have an extra fifteen years and so on. Because
he took credit for himself, בשביל הטוב בעיניך עשיתי, bishvil hatov be'einecha
asiti, I did what was good in your eyes, because of that
מה אות, ma os, that led to him sinning by that arrogance
that led to him sinning by demanding a sign because when ישעיהו
Yeshayahu told him
that God has listened to you and you will live and you'll
live another fifteen years, he said what will be the sign that
that will happen? What חוצפה chutzpah do you have? You just received
this amazing promise and this reprieve and you need a
sign? And he demanded then even a more arrogant he was given
a choice, do you want the sun to stand in its place
for ten hours or do you want it to move backwards for
ten hours? He said standing in its place is no big deal,
I want something that's much more visible, I want it to move
backwards. It's sort of an arrogance leading to an arrogance. ובשביל מה
אות, uvishvil ma os, and because he demanded a sign,
נכרים אכלו על שולחנו, nochrim achlu al shulchano, foreigners ate on his
table because it says
here that the king of Babylonia sent him these messengers when he
heard that he was sick. But maybe also it had to do
with this miracle that happened or whatever. Somehow either that arrogance led
to him receiving these emissaries from the king of
Babylon. אכלו על שולחנו ובשביל שנכרים אכלו על שולחנו, achlu al shulchano
uvishvil she'nochrim achlu al shulchano, it's all עבירה גוררת עבירה, aveira goreres
aveira, one sin leads to the next, and because they ate on
his table so גרם גלות לבניו, garam galus le'vanav, that caused ultimately
that his children would be sent into
exile because which is actually what happens that because he then he
shows them around and he shows them all his treasure houses and
then he received a prophecy that is said because you went ahead
and did this your kingship will be taken from you and all
of your beautiful things will be taken from you, you don't go
ahead and just display this and show off to these foreign kings.
So sort of one arrogance led to the next and ultimately it
led with the prophecy that the kingdom would be destroyed. גרם
גלות לבניו, garam galus le'vanav, it led to the exile of his
children. מסייע ליה לחזקיה, mesayei lei le'Chizkiya, this supports חזקיה, Chizkiya, interesting
חזקיה, Chizkiya, but this is
the
אמר חזקיה, damar Chizkiya, חזקיה Chizkiya says כל המזמן עובד כוכבים לתוך
ביתו, kol hamizamen akum letoch beiso, anybody who invites a non-Jew into
his house, remember a little while ago we were just talking about
the importance of extending food but now we're talking about a Jew
extending food to a non-Jew and you invite him into your house,
you're not just giving him food ומשמש עליו, umeshamesh elav, and you
then attend to him, so
you sort of demonstrate you see him as being superior, גרם גלות
לבניו, garam galus le'vanav, it ends with exile for your children. שנאמר,
shene'emar, as it says ובניך אשר יצאו ממך, uvanecha asher yetzu mimecha,
and this is ממש mamesh what the prophecy is after he does
this that he's told that your children which will come from you
אשר תוליד, asher toulid, that you'll sire יקחו, yikachu, they will be
taken והיו סריסים בהיכל מלך בבל, vehayu sarisim beheichal melech Bavel, and
they will be eunuchs
in the palace of the king of
בבל. Bavel. Now we're going to look at those פסוקים pesukim where
he actually went ahead and showed them and showed off to them
about these emissaries from the king of בבל. Bavel. וישמח עליהם חזקיהו,
vayismach aleihem Chizkiyahu, and Hezekiah was very joyous over them ויראם את
בית נכותו, vayar'em es beis nechoso, they showed him his house of
treasure. את הכסף ואת הזהב ואת הבשמים ואת השמן הטוב, et hakesef
veet hazahav veet habesamim veet hashemen hatov, gold and silver and, you
know, incense and, I mean, fragrances and good oil. אמר רבא. Amar
Rava. מאי בית נכתה? Mai Beis Nechoso? What does this mean בית
נכתה, Beis Nechoso, which is generally translated as treasure house? אשתו השקתה
להם. Ishto hishkasa lahem. So one interpretation is he had his wife,
you know, attend to them and that's not צנוע tzanua for his
wife to be attending to them also, you know, the queen attending
to these, to these emissaries. How exactly that's from the word nechoso,
רש"י Rashi tries to connect it, not exactly clear. ושמואל אמר בית
גנזיו הראה להם. Ushmuel amar Beis Ginzo her'alahem. His treasure house, which
is probably simpler in terms of context. ורבי יוחנן אמר זיון או
חזיון, V'rabbi Yochanan amar ziyan o chaziyan, like a weapon that could
destroy another weapon. Not exactly clear how he gets that from בית
נכתה הראה להם. Beis Nechoso her'alahem. Okay, now that we're talking about
that this sin led to the destruction of the בית המקדש, Beis
HaMikdash, you know, and already we've been sort of dealing with all
the evil kings and how, you know, they're evil, as we know
the stories in תנ"ך, Tanach, you know, led to the exile of
the ten tribes and the evil, you know, kings of in יהודה
Yehuda and led to the exile of, you know, יהודה ובנימין Yehuda
u'Binyamin and the destruction of the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So now
we're going to look at and do a דרש drash on the
פסוקים psukim in איכה. Eicha. Okay, and we're sort of going to
like go through it כסדר k'seder in order. So let's take a
look.
Okay,
איכה ישבה בדד. Eicha yashva vadad. How did this come that the
city Jerusalem now dwells alone? אמר רבא אמר רבי יוחנן מפני מה
לקו באיכה? Amar Rava amar Rabbi Yochanan mipnei ma laku b'Eicha? Why
were they punished with איכה? Eicha? Like that repeating theme of the
book of איכה? Eicha? מפני שעברו על שלושים וששה כריתות שבתורה Mipnei
she'avru al sheloshim v'shisha kritot shebaTorah because the gematria of איכה Eicha
is thirty-six, so it's because they transgressed the thirty-six, you know, violations
of the תורה, Torah, of the heavy sins that you get כרת
karet for. אמר רבי יוחנן מפני מה לקו בא"ב? Amar Rabbi Yochanan
mipnei ma laku b'alef-bet? And why were they punished like what's the
איכה Eicha which is the lamentation over the destruction, what's the significance
of it being like א"ב, alef-bet, you know, because that's the structure,
the acrostic structure and it sort of means from beginning to end.
So מפני שעברו על התורה שניתנה בא"ב mipnei she'avru al haTorah shenitna
b'alef-bet because they transgressed the תורה Torah that was given in א"ב,
alef-bet, you know, it was given in, I mean I don't know
what that means, it was given in Hebrew but okay, you know,
it was א"ב alef-bet represents the entirety of the Hebrew language, represents
the תורה, Torah, the enormity of their sin from א' alef through
ת', tav, and that's the significance.
Okay, ישבה בדד, yashva vadad, it now that's just an opening to
איכה, Eicha, the symbolism of the word, the symbolism of the structure
of the א"ב. alef-bet. Now we're going to look at each phrase.
איכה ישבה בדד, Eicha yashva vadad, אמר
רבא אמר רבי יוחנן אמר הקדוש ברוך הוא אני אמרתי, amar Rava
amar Rabbi Yochanan amar HaKadosh Baruch Hu ani amarti, I, so I
said says God, וישכון ישראל בטח בדד עין יעקב, vayishkon Yisrael betach
badad ein Yaakov, that Israel will dwell in security alone like, you
know,
the protection of Jacob, אל ארץ דגן ותירוש, el eretz dagan v'tirosh,
the land of grain, you know, and of wine, אף שמיו יערפו
טל, af shamav yaarfu tal, even its very heavens will drip with
dew.
So anyway that בדד badad was a בדד badad of secure, protected,
strong, not dependent on others, that's the ישבה בדד. yashva vadad. עכשיו
יהיה בדד מושבם, Achshav yehiye badad moshavam, now their dwelling place is
all alone meaning it's desolate, nobody is there. It's a different type
of being alone, alone and abandoned and desolate.
העיר רבתי עם, Ha'ir rabati am, the city that is, you know,
that used to be filled with people, היתה כאלמנה haita k'almana was
like it became like a widow. אמר רבא אמר רבי יוחנן שהיו
משיאין קטנה לגדול וגדולה לקטן. Amar Rava amar Rabbi Yochanan shehayu masiyin
katana l'gadol u'gdola l'katan. How was it so populous with people? That
they would marry off a younger woman to an older man and
an older woman to a younger man. Now what would this do?
רש"י Rashi says it doesn't literally mean a minor, means a younger
woman and an older man, younger man, older woman. So רש"י Rashi
says, you know, the way רש"י Rashi explained it is when people
get a little bit older, they're not just sort of hitting puberty,
it takes a few years until they become really fertile. So therefore,
you know, what they did was they matched somebody who was a
little less fertile with somebody who was more fertile so that people
would start to, both of those couplings, everybody would start having kids
right away. Whereas if you matched off a younger woman to a
younger man, at least the way רש"י Rashi tells it, again younger
meaning like close to the age of puberty, then it's going to
take a while before they can first start having kids. Okay, obviously
I don't know if this makes any sense based on our understanding
of medicine. But okay, and of the reality. But moving on.
היתה כאלמנה, Haita k'almana, became like a widow. אמר רב יהודה
אמר רב כאלמנה ולא אלמנה ממש, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav k'almana
v'lo almana mamash, like a widow but not literally a widow. What
does that mean? אלא כאישה שהלך בעלה למדינת הים ודעתו לחזור עליה,
Ela k'isha shehalach baala l'medinat hayam v'daato lachazor aleha, like a woman
whose husband went to a faraway
country but eventually he will return so she's... widow-like, but God has
not fully abandoned us, God will return. רבתי
בגוים שרתי במדינות היתה למס, Rabati bagoyim sarati bamdinot hayta lamas, right?
That was plentiful in the nations, great in the nations,
a prince amongst the countries or ruler of countries became now a
vassal. אמר רבא אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rava amar Rabbi Yochanan, כל
מקום שאתה הולך—so kol makom she'atah holech we're going to look at
שרתי במדינות, sarati bamdinot, you were princes in the countries. Wherever the
Jews would go, נעשים שרים לאדוניהם, nasim sarim l'adoneihem, they would become
princes to their masters. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, now we're going to
illustrate that. מעשה בשני בני אדם שנשבו בהר הכרמל, Ma'aseh bishnei bnei
adam she'nishbu b'har HaKarmel, there were two Jews that were taken captive
in the Mount Carmel. והיה שבאי מהלך אחריהם, v'haya shabbai m'halech achareihem,
and the captor was walking behind them, you know, they were taken,
they were going to be taken for slaves. אמרי אחד מהם לחבירו,
amrei echad mehem l'chaveiro, top of ק"ד עמוד ב', kuf daled amud
bet, so one of the Jewish captives said to his friend, or
Israelite captive, גמל שמהלך לפנינו סומא באחת מעיניו, gamal she'm'halech l'faneinu suma
b'achat me'einav, you know that camel that's walking in front of us,
it's blind in one of its eyes. It's like a little Shakespeare
moment—not Shakespeare, excuse me, Sherlock Holmes moment. וטעונה שתי נודות, u't'unah shtei
nodot, and it's carrying two skins, אחת של יין ואחת של שמן,
achat shel yayin v'achat shel shemen, one of wine and one of
oil. ושני בני אדם המנהיגים אותו אחד ישראל ואחד נכרי, ushnei bnei
adam hamanhigim oto echad Yisrael v'echad nachri, the two people that are
leading the donkey, אחד ישראל ואחד נכרי, echad Yisrael v'echad nachri, one
is a Jew and one is a non-Jew. אמר להן שבאי, Amar
lahen shabbai, so the captor overheard this and he said to them:
עם קשה ערף, am k'sheh oref, stiff-necked people. I don't know what
this has to do with being stiff-necked, but like maybe like חוצפה
chutzpah people, you think you're so smart. מאין אתם יודעים? Me'ayin atem
yod'im? How do you know this? Where do you get this from?
אמרו לו, Amru lo, they said to him: גמל מעשב שלפנינו מצד
שרואה אוכל, מצד שאינו רואה אינו אוכל. gamal me'asav she'l'faneinu mitzad she'ro'eh
ochel, mitzad she'eino ro'eh eino ochel. This camel is only eating from
one side of the road. It must be that it eats from
the side that it can see, so it must be that it's
blind in the other eye. וטעונה שתי נודות אחת של יין ואחת
של שמן, U't'unah shtei nodot achat shel yayin v'achat shel shemen, and
we know that it's carrying these two canteens, one of oil and
one of wine. How do we know that? Because יין מנטף ושוקע,
yayin metaftef v'shoke'a, wine drips and then gets absorbed into the ground,
ושמן מנטף וצף, v'shemen metaftef v'tzaf, and the oil drips and floats
on top of the ground. So when we walk after the camel,
we see a place in the ground that absorbed a liquid—presumably it
was also reddish and it was wine—and we see a place in
the ground that there's some oily substance on the surface. ושני בני
אדם המנהיגים אותו אחד נכרי ואחד ישראל, Ushnei bnei adam hamanhigim oto
echad nachri v'echad Yisrael, these two people that are leading it, אחד
נכרי ואחד ישראל, echad nachri v'echad Yisrael, one is a non-Jew, one
is a Jew. נכרי נפנה לדרך, Nachri nifneh laderech, the non-Jew relieves
himself on the way. וישראל נפנה לצדדים, V'Yisrael nifneh litzdadim, and the
Jew, if he has to relieve himself, he goes ahead and he
does it off of the main road because of צניעות. tzniyut. רדף
אחריהם, Radaf achareihem, so this captor ran after these, this camel party
that was in front of them, ומצא כדבריהם, u'matza k'divreihem, and he
asked them what's the story, is your camel
blind, who are the people leading it, and he found out it
was exactly as the Jews had said. בא ונשק על ראשם, Ba
v'nashak al rosham, he came and he kissed them on their heads,
והביאם לביתם, v'hevi'am l'veitam, he brought them back to their home, ועשה
להם סעודה גדולה, v'asa lahem seuda gedola, and he made for them
a great feast. והיה מרקד לפניהם, V'haya merakid lifneihem, and he danced
in front of them. They became the שרים, sarim, they became the
masters, he became the servant. ואמר ברוך שבחר בזרעו של אברהם ונתן
להם מחכמתו, v'amar Baruch shebachar b'zaro shel Avraham v'natan lahem michochmato, and
he said: Blessed is the one that chose the seed of Abraham
and gave to them from His—God's—wisdom. ובכל מקום שהן הולכין נעשים שרים
לאדוניהם, U'v'chol makom she'hein holchin nasim sarim l'adoneihem, wherever they go, they
will become masters, you know, princes to those who would be their
masters. ופטרן והלכו לבתיהם לשלום, U'pitaran v'halchu l'vateihem l'shalom, and he released
them and they went to their home—it said before like they were
already
home—but okay. Anyway, they went back and they were fully free. So
that at least is how it was before the חורבן הבית. Churban
Habayis. Back to the פסוקים. psukim. So that was the איכה פסוק,
Eicha pasuk, איכה ישבה בדד. eicha yashva bdad. Okay, now we're to
the ב'. bet. בכה תבכה בלילה, Bachoh tivkeh balaylah, she shall surely
cry in the night. שתי בכיות הללו למה? Shtei bchiyot hallalu lama?
What's the double crying? אמר רבא אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rava amar
Rabbi Yochanan, אחד על מקדש ראשון ואחד על מקדש שני, echad al
Mikdash Rishon v'echad al Mikdash Sheni, one for the first בית המקדש,
Beis HaMikdash, one anticipating the destruction of the second בית המקדש. Beis
HaMikdash.
בלילה, Balaylah, for the night, על עסקי לילה, al iskei laylah, because
of, ultimately it ties back to the original sin that was done
at night. שנאמר ותשא כל העדה ויתנו את קולם ויבכו העם בלילה
ההוא, Shene'emar vatissa kol ha'edah vayitnu et kolam vayivku ha'am balaylah hahu,
they all cried—this is the חטא המרגלים—they chet hamiraglim all lifted up
their voice at that night, and they all wanted to return to
Egypt. You know, that was תשעה באב Tisha B'Av according to the
tradition, and that's what ultimately
is coming back to haunt them now. אמר רבא אמר רבי יוחנן
אותו היום אותו הלילה ליל תשעה באב היה, Amar Rava amar Rabbi
Yochanan oto hayom oto halaylah leil Tisha B'Av haya, that night was
the night of תשעה באב. Tisha B'Av. אמר להם הקדוש ברוך הוא
לישראל, Amar lahem Hakadosh Baruch Hu l'Yisrael, God said to the Jewish
people: אתם בכיתם בכיה של חנם ואני אקבע לכם בכיה לדורות, Atem
bchitem bchiya shel chinam v'ani ekba lachem bchiya l'dorot, you've cried for
no reason, and I will give you—make this night a night of
crying for future generations. Okay, so that's לילה, laila, that ultimately the
sin of that original night came back. דבר אחר בלילה, Davar acher
balaila, at night, crying at night, שכל הבוכה בלילה קולו נשמע shekol
habocheh balaila kolo nishma because, you know, it's the world is very
quiet at night. So when you cry at night, your voice is
heard at a great distance. So the crying of the people was
of, you know, of the destruction could be heard at a great
distance. דבר אחר Davar acher another explanation בלילה, balaila, שכל הבוכה בלילה
shekol habocheh balaila anybody who cries at night כוכבים ומזלות בוכים עמו
kochavim umazalos bochim imo it's like the very stars and constellations, you
know, you get a sense of the universe at night that you
don't have in the day because you can see all the stars
and constellations. So it's as though the entire cosmos are sharing in
your pain. דבר אחר בלילה, Davar acher balaila, שכל הבוכה בלילה השומע
קולו בוכה כנגדו. shekol habocheh balaila hashomea kolo bocheh kenegdo. That anybody
who cries at night because the sound is so clear and not,
you know, like, clouded by the day sounds, so it doesn't have
that static. So it's very, very clear sound. So somebody can—people who
hear it are very impacted by it and therefore they wind up,
you know,
being overwhelmed with sympathy and they wind up crying along with, בוכה
עמו. bocheh imo.
דבר אחר, Davar acher, we just did that. בוכה כנגדו. bocheh kenegdo.
מעשה באשה אחת ששכנותו של רבן גמליאל Maaseh b'isha achas sheshchenoso shel
Raban Gamliel there was a story about a woman who lived in
the neighborhood of רבן גמליאל Raban Gamliel שמת בנה shemes binah that
her son died והיתה בוכה עליו בלילה v'haysah bochah alav balaila and
she cried at night over her dead son. שמע רבן גמליאל קולה
ובכה כנגדה Shama Raban Gamliel kolah v'hochah kenegdah רבן גמליאל Raban Gamliel
heard her crying and he couldn't help but to cry along with
her. עד שנשרו ריסי עיניו Ad shenishru risei einav to the point
that his very eyelashes fell out. למחר הכירו בו תלמידיו L'machar hikiru
bo talmidav the next day the students saw that his lashes had
fallen down, his eyes were red, they figured out what was happening.
They didn't want their great master to be so, you know, pained
and troubled. והוציאוה משכנותו V'hotziuha mishchunaso and they removed her from his
neighborhood. Doesn't sound fair that they're punishing her, but we can maybe
imagine that they removed her to an even better lodgings, but it
was not good for him that she was in the neighborhood.
Okay, continuing.
ודמעתה על לחיה V'dimasah al lochayah her tears on her cheek. אמר
רב אמר רבי יוחנן Amar Rav Amar Rabbi Yochanan כאשה שבוכה על
בעל נעוריה k'isha shebochah al baal neurim ha like a woman who
cries for the husband of her youth because לחיה lochayah רש"י Rashi
says is like moistness, you know, somebody still has the freshness of
youth. So the crying is for the losing the husband of the
youth. שנאמר Shene'emar and like the פסוק pasuk says, many of us
know it from the קינה, kinah, but ultimately from the פסוק, pasuk,
אלי כבתולה חגרת שק על בעל נעוריה eli k'visulah chogeras sak al
baal neurah a woe, a wailing for, for like a virgin who
is, you know, girding a sackcloth על בעל נעוריה al baal neurah
for the husband of her youth that is lost to her. היו
צריה לראש Hayu tzareha l'rosh her enemies became the head. אמר רב
אמר רבי יוחנן Amar Rav Amar Rabbi Yochanan back to איכה, Eichah,
כל המציק לישראל נעשה ראש. kol hameitzik l'Yisrael naasah rosh. Anybody who
causes, you know, who oppresses the Jewish people becomes a head. Now,
you don't want to let that line get out. That sounds like
it would be good advice to oppress the Jewish people, but the
general understanding is, you know, God, you know, out of respect to
us, God would not allow a nation oppress us unless they were
a mighty nation. Which is one way of understanding it, very difficult
line. שנאמר Shene'emar as the פסוק pasuk says, because
כי לא מועף לאשר מוצק לה ki lo muaf laasher mutzak lah
because there will be no, the way the גמרא Gemara is going
to read it is weariness to the one who causes, you know,
inflicts suffering, כעת הראשון הקל ארץ זבולון וארץ נפתלי, ka'eis harishon hekeil
eretz Zevulun v'eretz Naftali, originally it was like lighter in זבולון Zevulun
and נפתלי Naftali והאחרון הכביד, v'haacharon hichbid, and now at the last
one became heavier, דרך הים עבר הירדן גליל הגוים. derech hayam ever
hayarden gelil hagoyim. Okay, anyway, it's the end of the פסוק, pasuk,
but the key is the first part of it. אמר רב אמר
רבי יוחנן Amar Rav Amar Rabbi Yochanan כל המציק לישראל kol hameitzik
l'Yisrael whoever is—oppresses Israel or brings pain to Israel, אינו עיף. eino
ayeif. It's like they never become tired, you know, it feels to
us I think you could say that they never weary, like they
keep on oppressing us, killing us, doing all these horrible things, and
they never get weary of doing it, אינו עיף. eino ayeif. Okay,
so and that's לא מועף לאשר מוצק לה. lo muaf laasher mutzak
lah.
By the way, the גר"א Gra understands that this דרש drash on
this פסוק pasuk is not going to prove the previous point about
becomes a head, you know, that if you pain Israel you become
a head or you are a mighty nation, but it's a separate
point that the anti-Semites and those who want to kill us and
those who oppress never seem to grow tired. Back to the פסוקים
psukim in איכה, Eichah, לא אליכם כל עוברי דרך lo aleichem kol
ovrei derech this should not happen to you all those passers-by. אמר
רב אמר רבי יוחנן Amar Rav Amar Rabbi Yochanan מכאן לקובלנא מן
התורה. mikan l'kuvlanah min haTorah. From here you see the idea of
complaint from the תורה. Torah. Now what does it mean complaint? So,
I mean the whole איכה Eichah is a complaint, like a, you
know, it's a קינה, kinah, a lament. But anyway רש"י Rashi explains
what it really means is that when you are bemoaning your own
tragedies and your own צרות, tzaros, you should actually say but it
should not befall you. So קובלן kuvlan רש"י Rashi actually says like
as a way of like, like protecting the other person. I do
not mean that this—God, God willing none of this should happen to
you.
כל עוברי דרך, kol ovrei derech, all those who pass by. אמר
רב עמרם אמר רב, Amar Rav Amram amar Rav, עשוני כעוברי על
דת. asuni ke'ovrei al dat. They made me עוברי, ovrei, like transgressed,
so you know
it has made me, my punishments have made me demonstrate that I'm
like somebody who transgresses my religion.
ואילו בסדום כתיב, ve'ilu biSdom ketiv, because when it comes to סדום
Sodom it is written, וה' המטיר על סדום, vaHashem himtir al Sdom,
God caused you know fire and brimstone to come down to סדום.
Sodom. ואילו בירושלים כתיב, ve'ilu biYerushalayim ketiv, and by ירושלים Yerushalayim it
says, ממרום שלח אש בעצמותי וירדנה, mimarom shalach esh be'atzmotai vayirdena, from
on high God sent forth fire into my very bones and crushed
them or destroyed them. So the same idea of sending fire from
heavens that came to סדום Sodom came to us. So it's as
if we were greater sinners, you know, we were transgressors, which okay
they were transgressors but it was very demonstrated you know as bad
as סדום. Sodom. וכתיב ויגדל עון בת עמי מחטאת סדום. uketiv vayigdal
avon bat ami mechatat Sdom. The sin of my people was greater
than the sin of סדום. Sodom. וכי משוא פנים יש בדבר? vachi
maso fanim yesh badavar? And the גמרא Gemara says okay if that's
really true that it was greater than the sin of סדום Sodom
then why then God should not show any favoritism. So why weren't
they punished as bad as סדום Sodom was punished? You know סדום
Sodom was totally destroyed. Why would they not punished as badly? So
אמר רבה אמר רבי יוחנן מדה יתירה היתה בירושלים שלא היתה בסדום.
amar Rabbah amar Rabbi Yochanan midah yeteirah hayetah biYerushalayim shelo hayetah biSdom.
There was something special in ירושלים Yerushalayim that was not in סדום.
Sodom. דאילו בסדום כתיב, de'ilu biSdom ketiv,
when it comes to סדום Sodom it says,
הנה זה היה עון סדום אחותך גאון שבעת לחם ויד עני ואביון
לא החזיקה. hineh zeh hayah avon Sdom achotech gaon sivat lechem veyid
ani ve'evyon lo hechezikah. You know it
had all of this bread, all of this wealth and it did
not support the poor and the destitute. That's by סדום. Sodom. ואילו
בירושלים כתיב, ve'ilu biYerushalayim ketiv, when it comes to ירושלים Yerushalayim it
says, ידי נשים רחמניות בשלו ילדיהן. yedei nashim rachmaniyot bishlu yaldeihen. The
hands of compassionate women cooked their own children. Now what is the
point of this comparison? So and רש"י Rashi gives a couple of
explanations. One is okay look at least, I mean this is so
Jewish to find this positive in this horrific image. Okay then it's
at least you know it's
סדום Sodom was stingy but the Jewish people in ירושלים Yerushalayim even
when they were cooking their own children they at least shared it
with the neighbor because the end of the פסוק pasuk speaks about
היו לברות למו, hayu levarot lamo, like that they would eat it
together with their neighbor. So at least we had some compassion even
you know at this time and care for the other even when
we're cooking our own children and that's why we were not punished
as badly as סדום. Sodom. That is one way of reading it,
very sort of bizarre and ironic. The other way is that it's
saying we had it much worse, we were punished worse than סדום.
Sodom. סדום Sodom was destroyed but they had wealth. Our destruction came
through great privation and suffering. So in a way it was not
favoritism. Okay, סלה כל אבירי ה' בקרבי. sillah kol abbirai Hashem bekirbi.
You God have like you know crushed all of my strong ones
in my midst. כאדם שאומר לחבירו נפסלה מטבע זו. ke'adam she'omer lechavero
nifsala matbeia zu. Like a person that says to his friend you
know that this coin became invalid. How does a coin become invalid?
It becomes flattened and the image on it becomes destroyed. So God
also you crushed all of my strong ones you made them like
flattened coins you destroyed them. פצו עליך פיהם patzu alaich pihem now
we're up to פ. peh. So we did למד lamed we're up
to פ. peh.
You know they opened up against me against ירושלים Yerushalayim their mouths
the enemy. אמר רבה אמר רבי יוחנן בשביל מה הקדים פ לעין?
amar Rabbah amar Rabbi Yochanan bishvil mah hikdim peh le'ayin? It's very
interesting in איכה Eicha the פ peh comes before the עין ayin
in the acrostic. Now it could just be that you know at
that time maybe the order of the alphabet wasn't totally fixed but
we're going to make a דרשה derasha on it because for us
the עין ayin comes before the פ. peh. So why in איכה
Eicha does the פ peh come before the עין? ayin? בשביל מרגלים
bishvil meraglim because it's ultimately getting payback for the sin of the
מרגלים meraglim שאמרו בפיהם מה שלא ראו בעיניהם. she'amru befihem mah shelo
ra'u be'eineihem. They said with their פה, peh, their mouth, what they
didn't see with their עין, ayin, their eye. Their mouth came before
their eye. They made up their report, they told something they did
not see.
Okay now
not a פסוק pasuk from איכה Eicha but on the same theme,
אוכלי עמי אכלו לחם ה' לא קראו. ochlei ami achlu lechem Hashem
lo kara'u. Those who consume my people like they were consuming bread
they did not call out to God. אמר רבה אמר רבי יוחנן
כל האוכל מלחמן של ישראל טועם טעם לחם. amar Rabbah amar Rabbi
Yochanan kol haohel milachman shel Yisrael toeim ta'am lechem. Whoever eats from
the bread of
ישראל Yisrael really tastes what good bread is. Meaning like our enemies
love to eat from our food to steal from our food is
the way רש"י Rashi understands it or whatever. When they take from
our food they taste the real taste of bread. Now ושאינו אוכל
מלחמן של ישראל אינו טועם טעם לחם. veshe'eino ochel milachman shel Yisrael
eino toeim ta'am lechem. And if you know you're not eating Jewish.
bread, you never really tasted good bread. Now, why did this happen
that our enemies stole and took our bread? השם לא קראו Hashem
lo kara'u because we did not call out to God. רבא אמר
אלו הדיינים, Rava amar elu hadayanim, these are the judges that they
did not feel that God was in their midst and they did
not bring about true justice.
ושמואל אמר, uShmuel amar, Shmuel says אלו מלמדי תינוקות. elu melamdei tinokot.
No, these were school teachers that they were not having the kids,
like, להקריא, lehakri, to make the kids read פסוקים. psukim. That was
what מלמדי תינוקות melamdei tinokot would do, and they were being lazy
and therefore they were not being diligent on their jobs. Okay, that
is now our דרשה drasha on פסוקים psukim from איכה. Eicha. Now
we get back to who's on the list and who's not on
the list and finally who made up the list. So let's take
a look. מי מנאן, mi mana'an, who did the counting? אמר רב
אשי, amar Rav Ashi, אנשי כנסת הגדולה מנאום. Anshei Knesset HaGedolah mana'um.
It was the people of the Great Assembly at the beginning of
the second בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. They were the ones that actually
decided who are we going to list as people that don't have
a portion to the world to come. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב
ביקשו עוד למנות אחד. amar Rav Yehudah amar Rav bikshu od limnos
echad.
They wanted to count one more person. Who was it? We're not
even saying his name out of respect to him. שלמה המלך, Shlomo
HaMelech, because, you know, he worshipped... simple meaning of the פסוקים, psukim,
you know, his wives led him astray to idolatry and so on.
So באה דמות דיוקנו ba'ah dmut dyukno of his father, the icon...
דיוקן dyukan is the name of what, like icon, the image of
his father, of דוד David came to him...
excuse me, not to him, not to Shlomo, came to them, came
to the members of the כנסת הגדולה. Knesset HaGedolah. Okay? ונשתטח לפניהם
venishtachah lifneihem
and prostrated himself in front of the members of the אנשי כנסת
הגדולה. Anshei Knesset HaGedolah. ולא השגיחו עליו, velo hishgichu alav,
they said, "Sorry, we're going to count Shlomo in our list." באה
אש מן השמים, ba'ah esh min hashamayim, a fire came from heaven
ולחכה אש בספסליהם velichecha esh besafseleihem
and it charred, you know, the chairs that they were sitting on.
ולא השגיחו עליה, velo hishgichu aleha, they didn't pay attention to it.
It's sort of like the לא בשמים היא lo bashamayim hi story,
except this is not about הלכה, halacha, this is about deciding who
gets עולם הבא. Olam HaBa. יצתה בת קול ואמרה, yatzta bas kol
ve'amrah, a heavenly voice came out and said... ואמרה להם ve'amrah lahem
and said to them: חזית איש מהיר במלאכתו, chazita ish mahir bimlachto,
have you seen a person that is diligent in his work? לפני
מלכים יתייצב, lifnei melachim yityatzev, he will stand before kings. בל יתייצב
לפני חשוכים, bal yityatzev lifnei chashuchim, he will not stand before darkened
ones. מי, mi, so who does this referring to? שלמה. Shlomo. מי
שהקדים ביתי לביתו, mi shehikdim beiti leveito, he was diligent in his
work. He built the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash before he built his
house. ולא עוד אלא שביתי בנה בשבע שנים וביתו בנה בשלוש עשרה
שנה. velo od ela shebeiti banah besheva shanim uveito banah bishlosh esreh
shanah. My house he worked at diligently and he got it done
in seven. His own house he did not put in as much
effort; it took thirteen years. Such a person לפני מלכים יתייצב lifnei
melachim yityatzev will stand before kings, meaning standing in גן עדן. Gan
Eden. בל יתייצב לפני חשוכים, bal yityatzev lifnei chashuchim, not in front
of the darkened ones, not in גיהנום. Gehenom. ולא השגיחו עליה, velo
hishgichu aleha, they ignored the בת קול. Bas Kol. יצתה בת קול
ואמרה, yatzta bas kol ve'amrah, finally another בת קול Bas Kol came
out and said: המעמך ישלמנה, hime'imach yeshalmenah,
is it, you know, are you the ones to pay him back?
כי מאסת ki ma'asta because you have found... you have despised it.
כי אתה תבחר ולא אני, ki atah tivchar velo ani, do you
think you choose and not me? I, God, get to choose who
gets עולם הבא. Olam HaBa. Okay? Which is a great end here
to this, we'll stop here, which is it's very nice that the
אנשי כנסת הגדולה, Anshei Knesset HaGedolah, like, created the list, but do
they get to determine who gets עולם הבא Olam HaBa or in
the end God says, you know, guys, you might be making your
list, but it's not you who decides, it's me who decides. And
that again gets back to the question before about, you know, whether
this list is really ultimately who does... like, like what... who is
and isn't on this list is a question of who they chose
to list, but some people they didn't list, but still, you know,
that doesn't mean objectively they're not going to get... they will get
עולם הבא Olam HaBa or they won't get עולם הבא. Olam HaBa.
So, you know, very interesting this act of creating the list and
what it actually says about the metaphysical fate, you know, or the
eschatological fate, the future fate of these people.